上一节我们解释了什么是公钥加密系统
In the last segment, we explained what is
a public key encryption system. And we
我们定义了安全的公钥加密系统是什么意思
defined what it means for a public key
encryption system to be secure. If you
如果大家记得，我们要求对抗主动攻击的安全性。特别地
remember, we required security against
active attacks. And in particular, we
我们定义了选择密文安全，作为我们的目标。
本周，我们组建两个
defined chosen cipher text security as our
goal. This week, we're gonna construct two
公钥加密系统的家族，它们都是选择密文安全的
families of public key encryption systems
that are chosen cipher text secure. And in
本节我们开始构建公钥加密
this segment, we're gonna start by
constructing public key encryptions from,
从一个叫做陷门置换的概念出发
a concept called a trapdoor
permutation. So let's start by defining a
那么我们先定义一个广义的概念叫做陷门函数。
什么是陷门函数？
general concept called a trapdoor
function. So what is a trapdoor function?
陷门函数是一个函数，从集合X映射到集合Y
Well, a trapdoor function basically is a
function that goes from some set X to some
它定义为三个算法
set Y. And it's really defined by a triple
of algorithms. There's a generation
它们是：一个通用的算法，函数f，和函数f的逆
algorithm, the function f, and the inverse
of the function f. So the generation
那么这个通用算法，当你运行它时，它会生成一对密钥
algorithm, basically what it does when you
run it, it will generate a key pair, a
一个公钥和私钥。这个公钥定义了一个
public key and a secret key. The public
key is gonna define a specific function
从集合X映射到集合Y的特定函数。然后私钥定义了
from the set X to the set Y. And then the
secret key is going to define the inverse
这个函数的逆，从集合Y映射到集合X。那么这里的想法是
function now from the set Y to the set
X. So the idea is that you can evaluate
你可以使用公钥PK计算这个函数在任意点的值，
你可以使用私钥SK来计算函数的逆
the function at any point using a public key
PK and then you can invert that function
我说逆是什么意思？更为精确地
using the secret key, SK. So what do I
mean by inversion? More precisely, if we
如果我们看这个密钥生成算法G生成的公钥、私钥对
look at any public key and secret key pair
generated by the key generation algorithm
如果我计算函数在点X的值
G, then it so happens that if I evaluate
the function at the point X, and then I
然后我计算所得点的逆，我应该获得原点X
evaluate the inverse at the resulting
point, I should get the original point X
大家应该想象出，有这么个大集合X
back. So the picture you should have in
your mind, is there is this big set X and
和大集合Y，然后这个函数会把X中的任意点映射成Y中的点
this big set Y And then, this function
will map any point in X to a point in Y,
这一步可以使用公钥完成。那么X中的任一点
and this can be done using the public key.
So again any point in X can be mapped, to
可被映射到Y中的一个点。然后如果某人有私钥
a point in Y. And then if someone has the
secret key, then basically they can go in
就可以用这个私钥SK做相反的方向
the reverse direction by applying, this
secret key sk. So now that we
现在我们理解了什么是陷门函数，我们来定义
understand what a trapdoor function is,
let's define what it means for a trapdoor
安全的陷门函数的意思。那么我们说这个三元组
(G,F,F^-1)是安全的
function to be secure. And so we'll say
that this triple, (G, F, F inverse), is secure
如果事实上这个函数F(PK,.)是所谓的单向函数
if in fact this function F(PK, .) is what's
called a one way function. And let me
我们来解释什么是单向函数。其想法是
explain what a, what is a one way
function. The idea is that basically the
这个函数可以在任一点计算，但求它的逆是困难的
function can be evaluated at any point,
but inverting it is difficult without the
如果没有私钥SK的话。那么我们来更为精确地定义，
通常我们使用一个游戏来定义之
secret key SK. So let's define that more
precisely. As usual we define that using a
这里我们有我们的游戏，在挑战者和攻击者之间
game. So here we have our game between the
challenger and the adversary. And the game
游戏如下进行。挑战者生成一个公钥和私钥
proceeds as follows. Basically the
challenger will generate a public key and
他们会生成一个随机X，挑战者把公钥发给攻击者
a secret key. And then they will generate
a random X. It will send the public key
它会计算函数在点X的值
over to the adversary and then it will
evaluate the function at the point X and
然后把所得结果Y也发给攻击者
send the resulting Y also to the
adversary. So all the adversary gets to
那么攻击者看到一个公钥，定义了这个函数是什么
see is just a public key, which defines
what the function is, and then he gets to
然后攻击者看到这个函数在一个随机点X处的像，他的目标是求
see the image of this function on a random
point X and is goal is basically to invert
这个函数在这个点Y处的逆。那么他输出某个X'
the function at this point Y. Okay, so he
outputs some X prime. And we said that the
我们说过，这个陷门函数是安全的，如果
攻击者求出在点Y处的逆的概率
trapdoor function is secure if the
probability that the ad, adversary inverts
是可以忽略的。换句话说，给定Y
the given at point y is negligible. In
other words, given y the probability that
攻击者能够算出Y的原像的概率事实上是可忽略的
the adversary's able to alter the pre
image of y is in fact a negligible
如果这点对所有有效算法都成立，那么我们说
probability and if that's true for all
efficient algorithms then we say that this
这个陷门函数是安全的。那么再抽象点
trapdor function is secure. So again
abstractly, it's a really interesting
这是个有趣的概念，你可以非常容易地从正向计算这个函数
concept in that you can evaluate the
function in the forward direction very
但没人能从反方向计算这个函数
easily. But then no one can evaluate the
function in the reverse direction unless
除非他们有这个陷门私钥SK，有了SK
they have this trapdoor, the secret key
SK, which then all of a sudden lets them
使得他们突然间就能很容易地求这个函数的逆了。
那么使用陷门函数的概念
invert the function very, very easily. So
using the concept of a trapdoor function,
不难构建一个公钥加密系统，我来告诉大家怎么做
it's not too difficult to build a public key encryption system, and let me show you how
这里我们有我们的陷门函数(G,F,F^-1)
to do it. So here we have we our trapdoor
function, (G, F, and F inverse). The other
我们需要的另一个工具是一个对称加密机制
tool that we are going to need is a symmetric encryption scheme, and I'm going to
我要假设这个加密机制对主动攻击是安全的
assume that this encryption scheme is actually
secure against active attacks, so in
那么特别地，我需要提供认证加密
particular I needed to provide
authenticated encryption. Notice that the
注意对称加密系统取K中的密钥，陷门函数取X中的元素为输入
symmetric encryption system takes keys in
K and the trapdoor function takes inputs
这是两个不同的集合，所以我们需要哈希函数
in X. Those are two different sets and so
we're also gonna need the hash function.
从X映射到K。换句话说，它把集合X中的元素映射成密钥
That goes from X to K. In other words, it
maps elements in the set X into keys for
用于对称加密系统。现在我们一旦有了这3个原件
the symmetric encryption systems. And now
once we have these three components, we
我们就可以如下构建公钥加密系统
can actually construct the public key encryption system as follows: so the key
公钥加密系统的密钥生成，与陷门函数的密钥生成
generation for the public key encryption
system is basically exactly the same as
是完全一样的。那么我们为陷门函数运行算法G
the key generation for the trap door
function. So we run G for the trap door
我们获得一个公钥和私钥，这些将是
function, we get a public key and a secret
key. And those are gonna be the public and
公钥加密系统的公钥和私钥。那我们怎么加、解密？
secret keys for the public key encryption
system. And how do we encrypt and decrypt? Let's
我们从加密开始。加密算法取一个公钥和明文为输入
start with encryption. So the encryption
algorithm takes a public key and a message
它会生成一个集合X里的随机元素x
as input. So what it will do is it will
generate a random X from the set capital
然后它会对随机元素x应用这个陷门函数，获得y
X. It will then apply the trapdoor
function to this random X, to obtain Y. So
那么y是x在陷门函数下的像
Y is the image of X under the trapdoor
function. Then it will go ahead and
然后它会生成一个对称密钥，通过取x的哈希值。
那么这是对称加密系统的对称密钥
generate a symmetric key by hashing X. So
this is a symmetric key for the symmetric
最终它加密明文m，使用刚刚生成的密钥
key system. And then finally it encrypts
the plain text message 'm' using this key that was
然后它输出它刚刚计算得到的值y
just generated. And then it outputs the
value Y that it just computed, which is
也就是x的像，与m在对称密码下的加密结果一并输入
the image of X, along the encryption under
the symmetric system of the message M. So
那么这就是加密的工作流程。我想再强调一次
that's how encryption works. And I want to
emphasize again that the trapdoor function
这个陷门函数只用于随机值x，而信息本身
is only applied to this random value X,
whereas the message itself is encrypted
是用对称密钥系统加密的，使用根据我们随机选的x推出的密钥
using a symmetric key system using a key
that was derived from the value X that we
那么现在我们理解了加密，我们再看解密
chose at random. So now that we understand
encryption, let's see how to decrypt.
解密算法取私钥和密文作为输入
While the decryption algorithm takes a
secret key as input, and the ciphertext.
密文本身包含两个部分，值y和C
The ciphertext itself contains two
components, the value Y and the value C.
首先我们应用陷门函数的逆变换
So the first step we're gonna do, is we're
gonna apply the inverse transformation,
逆向陷门函数作用于值y，会返回给我们
the inverse trap door function to the
value Y, and that will give us back the
在加密时选择的随机x。那么现在我问大家
original X that was chosen during
encryption. So now let me ask you, how do
我们如何从这个刚刚得到的x推导出对称的解密密钥K？
we derive the symmetric decryption key K
from this X that we just obtained? Well,
这是个简单问题。我们再次对x取哈希值
so that's an easy question. We basically
hash X again. That gives us K just as
就能给我们与加密时得到的一样的密钥K。现在
我们有了这个对称加密密钥
during encryption. And now that we have
this symmetric encryption key we can apply
我们就可以应用对称解密算法来解密密文C了
the, the symmetric decryption algorithm to
decrypt the ciphertext C. We get the
我们获得了最初的明文M，作为我们的解密输出
original message M and that's what we
output. So, that's how the public key
这就是公钥加密系统的工作过程，这个陷门函数
encryption system works were this trap
door function is only used for encrypting
只用于加密一个随机值x，而实际的明文信息
some sort of a random value X and the
actual message is encrypted using the
是使用对称系统加密的。用图来看，我们有明文M
symmetric system. So in pictures here, we
have the message M obviously the plain
显然明文可以很长，那么我们这里的密文部分
text could be quite large. So, here we
have the body of the deciphered text which
可以是很长的，它是使用对称系统加密的
can be quite long is actually encrypted
using the symmetric system. And then again
然后我再强调一下，对称系统的密钥是x的哈希
I emphasize that the key for the
symmetric system is simply the hash of X.
然后密文的开头就是我们选的随机数x的陷门函数值
And then the header of ciphertext is simply
this application of the trapdoor
而在解密过程中
function to this random X that we picked.
And so during decryption what happens is
我们首先解密密文开头，获得x，然后我们解密
we first decrypt the header to get X and
then we decrypt the body using the
密文部分，使用对称系统，获得最初的明文M
symmetric system to actually get the
original plain text M. So as usual when I
通常当我给大家看一个像这样的系统时，
大家显然想验证，解密的确是
show you a system like this, obviously you
want to verify that decryption in fact is
加密的逆。但更重要地，大家想问
the inverse of encryption. But more
importantly you want to ask why is this
为什么这个系统是安全的。事实上有一个漂亮的安全性定理
system secure. And in fact there's a nice
security theorem here that says. That if
告诉我们，如果开始的陷门函数是安全的，换句话说
the trap door function that we started
with is secure. In other words, that's a
这是个单向函数，如果攻击者没有私钥的话
one way function if the adversary doesn't
have a secret key. The symmetric
对称加密系统提供了认证加密
encryption system provides authenticated
encryption. And the hash function is a
哈希函数是一个随机神谕，意思是它是个随机函数
random oracle, which simply means that
it's a random function from the set X to
从集合X映射到密钥空间K。那么随机神谕是某种理想化的模型
the set of keys K. So a random oracle is
some sort of an idealization of, what a
也是一个哈希函数应具备的性质。当然在实际中
hash function is supposed to be. In
practice, of course, when you come to
当你要实现一个像这样的系统时，你就使用SHA-256
implement a system like this, you would
just use, SHA-256, or any of the
或任何本课程里讨论过的其他哈希函数。
那么在这三个条件下
other hash functions that we discussed in
class. So, under those three conditions in
事实上，我们刚刚讨论的系统是选择密文安全的
fact the system that we just described is
chosen cipher text secure so it is CCA
所以它是CCA安全的。这个ro表示这个安全性
secure, the little ro here just denote the
fact that security is set in what's called
是建立在所谓的随机神谕模型上的。但这只是一个细节，
对我们这里的讨论来说并不重要
a random oracle model. But, that's a detail
that's actually not so important for
我想让大家记住的是，如果陷门函数
discussion here, what I want you to
remember is that if the trap door function
是安全的陷门函数，对称加密系统是安全的
is in fact a secure trap door function. The
symmetric encryption system is secure
能抵抗篡改，所以它提供了认证加密
against tampering so it provides
authenticated encryption. And H
而H某种意义上讲是个好哈希函数，它是一个随机函数
is in some sense a good hash function.
It's a random function, which in practice
在实际中你就使用SHA-256，那么事实上我们刚刚展示的系统
you would just use SHA-256, then in
fact the system that we just showed is CCA
是CCA安全的，选择密文安全的。我应该告诉大家
secure, is chosen ciphertext secure. I should
tell you that there's actually an ISO
实际上有一个ISO标准，定义了这种公钥加密模式
standard that, defines this mode of
encryption, of public encryption. ISO
ISO代表国际标准组织。事实上
stands for International Standards
Organization. So in fact this particular
这个特定的系统已经被标准化了，是个好东西可以用
system has actually been standardized, and
this is a fine thing to use. I'll refer to
我会在未来几节里提到这个ISO加密。为了总结本节
this as the ISO encryption in the next few
segments. To conclude this segment, I want
我想警告大家，有一种错误使用陷门函数来构建的
to warn you about an incorrect way of
using a trapdoor function to build a
公钥加密系统。事实上这种方法可能是人们第一个想到的
public key encryption system. And in fact
this method might be the first thing that
但是它是完全不安全的。那么我来告诉大家
comes to mind, and yet it's completely
insecure. So let me show you, how not to
为什么不要用陷门函数来加密。我们首先能想到的是
encrypt using a trapdoor function. Well
the first thing that might come to mind
直接对明文M使用陷门函数
is, well, let's apply the trapdoor
function directly to the message M. So we
那么我们就使用陷门函数来加密明文M
encrypt simply by applying a function to
the message M, and we decrypt simply by
然后使用F的逆函数来解密密文C，以还原明文M
applying F inverse to the ciphertext C to
recover the original message M. So
那么事实上，解密是加密的逆过程
functionally, this is in fact, decryption
is the inverse of encryption, and yet this
然而这是完全不安全的，有很多的原因
is completely insecure for many, many
different reasons. The easiest way to see
最简单的方法来证明它不安全，在于这是一个确定的加密
that this is insecure, is that it's
simply, this is deterministic encryption.
大家注意这里没有随机性被使用到。当我们加密一个明文M
You notice there is no randomness being
used here. When we encrypt a message
由于算法是确定的
M, and since it is deterministic, it's cannot possibly be
它不可能是语义安全的。但事实上，如我所说，
当我们将这个陷门函数具象化
semantically secure. But in fact, as I
said, when we instantiate this trap door
使用特定的实现，例如RSA陷门函数
function with particular implementations,
for example with the RSA trap door
那么这种机制会有很多可能的攻击
function, then there are many, many
attacks that are possible on this
所以大家永远不要使用它
particular construction, and so you should
never, ever, ever use it, and I'm gonna
本章我将反复重申这一点，事实上在下一节里
repeat this throughout this module, and in
fact in the next segment I'll show you a
我会给大家看很多针对这种实现的攻击
number of attacks on this particular
implementation. Okay so, what I would like
我想让大家记住，你应该使用像ISO标准这样的加密系统
you to remember is that you should be
using an encryption system like the ISO
永远不要对明文M直接使用陷门函数
standard, and you should never apply the
trap door function directly to the message M.
尽管在下节我们会看到其他加密方法
Although in the next segment we'll
see other ways to encrypt using a trap
使用了陷门函数，而且也是正确的。但这种方法
door function that are also correct, but
this particular method is clearly, clearly
显然是错误的。那么现在我们理解了怎样构建公钥加密
incorrect. Okay, so now that we understand
how to build public key encryption
基于一个陷门函数。下一个问题是如何构建陷门函数
given a trap door function, the next
question is how to construct trap door
我们下节讨论之
functions, and we're going to do that in
the next segment.